Guide to the Parliamentary Speeches, Negotiations, Etc.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Parliamentary speeches, negotiations, etc., (most from 1640-1641)]
1599-1641
OSBORN FB161
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.19
(1 volume)
Manuscript, primarily in Browne's hand, though numerous items are in other hands, of a collection of about 74 items, primarily on Parliamentary subjects and mostly dated 1641. Items include extracts from Parliamentary journals; speeches by James I and Charles I; discussions concerning Scotland; notes on the speeches of Edward, Earl of Conway and Sir John Coke; Parliamentary resolutions declaring ship money to be illegal; a protestation by the House of Commons vowing to uphold the Church of England against Jesuits and "Papists"; and numerous speeches concerning the trial of Thomas Wentworth, Earl of Strafford.
Browne, John, approximately 1608-1691
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn fb161. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Treason -- England; Trials -- England; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- Scotland; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1603-1649; Great Britain -- Religious life and customs -- 17th century; Scotland -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Commonplace books; Elizabeth, Queen of England, I, 1533-1603; Browne, John, approximately 1608-1691; Charles, King of England, I, 1600-1649; Coke, John, Sir, 1563-1644; Conway of Conway Castle, Edward Conway, Viscount, 1623-1683; Finch, John, Baron Finch of Fordwich, 1584-1660; Glanville, John, Sir, 1586-1661; Holles, Denzil Holles, Baron, 1599-1680; Pym, John, 1584-1643; Strafford, Thomas Wentworth, Earl of, 1593-1641; Vane, Henry, Sir, 1613-1662; Great Britain. Parliament; Great Britain. Parliament. House of Lords; Braye, Alfred Verney-Cave, Baron, Baron, 1849-1928 -- Bookplate
- Osborn fb161
  - ELIZABETH, QUEEN OF ENGLAND, 1533-1603
    - "Instructions for our Cousin and councellor Robert Earl of Essex E. Marshall of England, etc. Lieutenant and Governor general of the Kingdom of Ireland Given at Richmond the 29th of March 1599". (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      8 p.
      Contemporary MS copy.
      p.1-5.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Extracts and notes from the Journals of the House of Lords on the case of Edward Floyd (d.1648?), 1621 May 11-30] (Box 1)
      Autograph MS. The first four pages
      are missing. See LJ, III, under
      various dates.
      p.6-9.
  - JAMES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1566-1625
    - [The King's declaration to Parliament on breaking the Spanish treaties, 1623/4 Mar 23], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      4 p.
      Contemporary MS copy; Latin
      translation. LJ, III, 282 (in
      English).
      p.10-11.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Extracts from the Journals of the House of Lords, c.1603-1624], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      2 p.
      Autograph MS. Notes on conferences,
      meetings and messages between the
      two Houses.
      p.12-13.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Extracts and notes from the Journals of Parliament on messages and meetings between the two Houses, c.1565-1625] (Box 1)
      Autograph MS. From the reigns of
      Elizabeth I, James I, and Charles I.
      p.14-15.
  - CONWAY, EDWARD CONWAY, VISCOUNT, D.1631
    - [Notes on the speeches of Lord Conway and Sir John Coke (1563-1644) to both Houses, 1625 Aug 25] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS. Speeches on the
      King's need for supply for the war
      against Spain. LJ, III, 471.
      p.16-17
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Precedents of judgments upon delinquents; extracts from the Journals of the House of Lords, 1626-1628] (Box 1)
      Autograph MS. LJ, various dates.
      p.18-19.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1626.
    - [Order in the House of Lords concerning the fees due to the clerk and his assistants, 1626 June 5] (Box 1)
      1 p.
      MS, signed H.Elsynge. Also a list of
      peers who "have not payde, as yet".
      LJ, III, 682.
      p.20-22.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - "Notes out of the Journals concerning conferences between both Houses, 1628 June 13", [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Autograph MS. LJ, III, 853.
      p.22-23.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1628.
    - [Message to the King requesting that Dr Mainwaring's book be called in and burnt, 1628 June 16] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, III, 859.
      p.24-25.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's speech delivered to both Houses, 1640/1 Jan 23], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      6 p.
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 142.
      See p.36 for another copy, with some
      text variations.
      p.26-29.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - [Negotiations between the commissioners of the House of Lords and the Scottish commissioners, 1640/1 Jan 26] (Box 1)
      3 p.
      3 documents; 2 signed "Ad.Blair", 1
      in the hand of John Browne.
      Concerning a peace treaty to be
      granted to the Scots. LJ, IV, 145
      bound here out of order.
      p.30-35.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Additional copy of the King's speech to both Houses at Whitehall, 1640/1 Jan 23], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      See p.26. Text variations.
      p.36-41.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - [Resolution in the House of Lords declaring Ship Money illegal, in agreement with the House of Commons, 1640.1 Jan 20], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      2 MS copies in the hand of John
      Browne. LJ, IV, 136.
      p.42-45.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1641.
    - "The index of the Heads of the Scotch Commissioners demands" (Box 1)
      [1640/1 March 9]
      Contemporary MS, signed "Ad.Blair".
      See LJ, IV, 216 for a paper reported
      in the House of Lords 1641 April 14
      which includes many of the demands
      in this Index.
      p.46-47.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Notes on Parliamentary business, 1640/1 Feb 8-15], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Autograph MS. Draft notes, see
      LJ, iv, 155-173. Includes notes on a
      speech by Algernon Percy, 10th earl
      of Northumberland (1602-1668).
      p.48.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1641.
    - [The eighth demand of the Scots in the treaty between Scotland and England, requesting that the garrisons at Berwick and Carlisle be removed, 1640/1 Feb 10] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 159.
      p.49-50.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1641.
    - [The answer of the Scot's commissioners accepting the assistance granted by Parliament, 1640/1 Feb 5], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy in the hand of
      John Browne. LJ, IV, 153.
      p.51-52.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS.
    - [Extracts from the Lords' Journal, 1640/1 Feb 10 and 1673] (Box 1)
      Anonymous MS. On the introduction
      and ranking of Charles Longueville,
      12th baron of Grey (1612-1643) in
      the House of Lords. Note following
      on the ranking of Francis Lennard,
      14th baron Dacre (1619-1662).
      p.53.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's speech to both Houses at the passing of the Triennial Bill, 1640/1 Feb 16], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Cobbett, v.2, 714.
      f.54-55.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - [Resolutions in the House of Lords declaring Ship Money illegal and vacating the proceedings against John Hampden, 1640/1 Feb 27] (Box 1)
      Draft copy. LJ, IV, 173.
      p.55-56.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - [Order concerning the managing of evidence at the trial of Thomas Wentworth, 1st earl of Strafford (1593-1641), 1640/1 Mar 13], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      John Browne. LJ, IV, 184.
      p.56.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1641.
    - [Declaration of the Scot's commissioners concerning Church government, 1640/1 Mar 10], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      23 p.
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 216.
      Printed as pamphlet in 1641, now at
      Beinecke (call #; British Tracts,
      1641, Sco.8).
      p.57-68.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1641.
    - [Rules and procedure to be followed at the trial of the Earl of Strafford, agreed to by both Houses, 1640/1 Mar 13] (Box 1)
      2 contemporary MS copies,
      LJ, IV, 184.
      p.69-71.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - [Instructions concerning a conference with the House of Commons on the proceedings in the Earl of Strafford's trial, 1641 April 12], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Draft copy in the hand of John
      Browne. LJ, IV, 215.
      p.72.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1641.
    - [Paper on the need for immediate assistance to the Scottish Army, read in the House of Lords, 1640/1 Mar 17], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 187.
      p.73-74.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1641.
    - [Orders by Parliament regarding the oaths to be sworn by witnesses at the trial of the Earl of Strafford, 1640/1 Mar 19], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Browne. LJ, IV, 190.
      p.75-76.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - [Arguments concerning the impeachment and attainder of the Earl of Strafford, and the rights of judicature of the House of Lords, c.1641 April] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS. Perhaps a speech in
      the House of Lords.
      p.77-78.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - [Order unanimously admitting the protestation of the Lords on the Council at York against allegations made against them by the Earl of Strafford, 1640/1 Mar 15], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Draft copy. LJ, IV, 185.
      p.79-80.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1641.
    - [Answer to the House of Lords concerning attendance at the trial of the Earl of Strafford, 1640/1 Mar 16] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copies. CJ, 11, 105.
      p.81-84.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. JUDGES.
    - [Resolution of the judges on the rights of the Earl of Strafford in the examination of witnesses at his trial, 1641 April 10], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Draft copy. LJ, IV, 212. See p.203
      for a copy of the question put to
      the judges.
      p.85-86.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1640.
    - [Resolutions that the vote giving the King's supply precedency over other business was not a breach of the privileges of the House of Commons, 1640 Apr 29-30], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Draft copies in the hand of John
      Browne. LJ, IV, 73-74.
      p.87-88.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1640.
    - [The heads of a conference with the House of Commons agreed upon in the House of Lords, 1640 Apr 25], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      John Browne. LJ, IV, 68.
      p. 89-90.
  - FINCH, JOHN FINCH, 1ST BARON, 1584-1660
    - [Speech of the Lords Keeper at the opening of Parliament, with introductory remarks by the King, 1640 Apr 13], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      27 p.
      Contemporary MS copies, one
      incomplete. LJ, IV, 46.
      p.90-116.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS.
    - [Names of Receavours and Triers of Petitions in French, 1640 Apr 13] (Box 1)
      Browne. List amended 1661 May 18.
      LJ, iv, 48 & LJ, XI, 224.
      p.117-118.
  - FINCH, JOHN FINCH, 1ST BARON, 1584-1660
    - [Additional copy of p.90-116], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      p.119-134.
  - GLANVILLE, SIR JOHN, 1586-1661
    - [Speech of the Speaker of the House of Commons on his presentation to the King; followed by a reply by the Lord Keeper, 1640 Apr. 15], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 50.
      p.135-150.
  - FINCH, JOHN FINCH, 1ST BARON, 1584-1660
    - [The Lords Keeper's report on his declaration to both Houses on the need for supply, 1640 Apr 22], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copies.
      p.151-174.
  - VANE, SIR HENRY, 1589-1655
    - "A copy of Sir Henry Vane's paper sent from the House of Commons on Monday the 12th of April 1641" (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copies, one in the
      hand of John Browne.
      p.175-178.
  - MIDDLESEX, ENGLAND. COMMISSIONERS.
    - [Warrant for coat and conduct money for the County of Middlesex, 1640 June] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 273
      (questions about this warrant raised
      in Parliament). John Browne was one
      of the commissioners.
      p.179-180.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1640.
    - [Heads of the Scottish demands considered by Parliament, 1640 Dec 18] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 111.
      p.181-183.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1640.
    - [List of spiritual and temporal peers in Parliament, 1640] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 45.
      p.184.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's speech at the opening of Parliament, 1640 Nov 2], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Rushworth, v.4, 11.
      p.185-186.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1641.
    - [Resolution of the House of Commons on granting assistance to Scotland, 1640/1 Feb 4] (Box 1)
      CJ, II, 78 and LJ, IV, 151.
      p.187-188.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's answer to the Remonstrance of both Houses concerning the Jesuits, 1640/1 Feb 4], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 151.
      p.189-190.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1640.
    - [Message delivered by John Pym to the House of Lords, stating that the Commons intends to impeach the Earl of Strafford, 1640 Nov 11] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copies. LJ, IV, 88.
      p.191-193.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1640.
    - [Journal notes for 1640 Nov 14], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      MS in the hand of John Browne.
      Includes notes on the Earl of
      Strafford and the treaty with
      Scotland. LJ, IV, 91.
      p.194.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1640.
    - [Message to the House of Lords concerning the examination of witnesses at the trial of the Earl of Strafford, 1640 Nov 20], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 94.
      p.195-196.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1640.
    - [A paper by the Scots commissioners concerning the Scottish Army in the North of England, 1640 Dec 16] (Box 1)
      Reported in LJ, IV, 110.
      p.197-198.
  - PERCY, HENRY PERCY, BARON PERCY OF ALNWICK, D.1659
    - [Letter to the Earl of Northumberland on the Army Plot, 1641 June 14] (Box 1)
      Rushworth, v.4, 255.
      p.199-202.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - [A question put to the judges concerning the rights of the Earl of Strafford in the examination of witnesses at his trial, 1641 April 10], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      John Browne. LJ, IV, 212. See p.85
      and p.204 for the judges' answer.
      p.203
  - GREAT BRITAIN. JUDGES.
    - [The judges' opinion on the right of the Earl of Strafford to produce new evidence at his trial, 1641 Apr 10], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      John Browne. LJ, IV, 212.
      p.204-205.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1641.
    - [Conference concerning Sir Henry Vane's paper and evidence against the Earl of Strafford, 1641 Apr 12] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. CJ, II, 119.
      See p.175 this volume.
      p.205-206.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1641.
    - [Conference of both Houses about allowing the Earl of Strafford counsel in matter of law, 1641 Apr 15], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 217.
      p.207-208.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [The King's answer to Parliament concerning papists and the Irish Army, 1641 Apr 13] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 230.
      p.209-210.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1641.
    - [Protestation vowing to uphold the Church of England against the designs of Jesuits and papists, 1641 May 4] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 233.
      See p.213 this volume.
      p.211-212.
  - HOLLES, DENZIL, 1599-1680
    - [Speech on presenting the Protestation to the House of Lords, 1641 May 4], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      p.213-214.
  - WADSWORTH, JAMES
    - [Testimony against Sir John Suckling (1609-1642), 1641 May 4], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. Concerns the
      Army Plot and Suckling's raising of
      troops under cover of recruiting
      troops for Portugal.
      p.215-216.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - [Resolutions on the Bill of Attainder against the Earl of Strafford, 1641 May 5-7] (Box 1)
      3 Contemporary MS copies. These
      proceedings were deleted from the
      Lords Journals in 1661, but see
      marginal notes in LJ, IV, 235.
      p.217-222.
  - BROWNE, JOHN, D.1691
    - [Extracts from the records of the House of Lords, 1641 May 15-July 8], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Autograph MS. Notes on bills,
      committee meetings, etc, arranged in
      a list by date.
      p.223-224.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. JUDGES.
    - [A query of the judges of the King's Bench concerning the Act abolishing the Court of Star Chamber, 1641 July 24], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 327.
      p.225-226.
  - LITTLETON, EDWARD LITTLETON, 1ST BARON, 1589-1645
    - [Letter of thanks to the Lord General, Sir Thomas Fairfax, sent at the command of the House of Lords, 1641 Aug 17] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy, with
      corrections. LJ, IV, 367.
      p.227-228.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - [A question considered by a committee of the whole house concerning the liability of the judges of the Court of York, 1641 July 13], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Draft copy. See LJ, IV, 311 for
      the resolutions on this and other
      questions concerning the Court of
      York.
      p.228b.
  - CHARLES I, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, 1600-1649
    - [Message to the House of Lords concerning the King's commitment to levy soldiers for Spain, 1641 Aug 24], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 374,
      with variations.
      p.229.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF LORDS, 1641.
    - Order for the redress of the French Ambassador who was assaulted in his house, 1641 Aug 30], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Document, signed by John Browne.
      LJ, IV, 382.
      p.230-231.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1641.
    - [Ordinance declaring a day of public thanksgiving for the peace concluded between England and Scotland, 1641 Aug 27] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 379.
      p.232-233.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1640.
    - [Charge against the Earl of Strafford, 1640 Dec 16], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      11 p.
      Rushworth, v.8, 769.
      p.234-239.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT. HOUSE OF COMMONS, 1641.
    - [Message to the Lords to be carried to Sir Henry Vane concerning duties of foreign goods, 1641 Aug 30], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. CJ, II, 275.
      p.240-241.
  - GREAT BRITAIN. PARLIAMENT, 1641.
    - [An ordinance concerning the transporting of troops out of England and Ireland, 1641 Sept 9] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 394.
      p.242-243.
  - CONNELLY, OWEN
    - [Examination of Owen Connelly taken before the Lord Justices of Ireland concerning the Irish Rebellion.] (Box 1)
      LJ, IV, 415.
      p.244-245.
  - PYM, JOHN, 1584-1643
    - [A report to the House of Lords of Pym's message at a Conference about depriving the bishops of their votes in Parliament, 1641 Oct 28], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 407.
      p.246-247.
  - CONYERS, SIR JOHN
    - [Examination of Conyers taken before the committee of the House of Lords, 1641 Oct 29], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. Testimony
      about the Second Army Plot.
      Reported in LJ, IV, 410.
      p.248-249.
  - LEGG, WILLIAM
    - [Examination of Legg taken before the committee of the House of Lords, 1641 Oct 30], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Reported in LJ, IV, 411.
      p.250-251.
  - GIUSTINIAN, GIOVANNI
    - [Complaint of the Venetian Ambassador to the House of Lords about his letters being opened, 1641 Nov 12], [n.d.] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 435.
      p.254-255.
  - SCOTLAND. COMMISSIONERS IN LONDON, 1641.
    - [Paper demanding an answer to their propositions for a treaty with Parliament, 1641 Dec 20] (Box 1)
      Contemporary MS copy. LJ, IV, 482.
      p.256.